Anatole France Collection
Anatole France Collection
1877-1918
France, Anatole, 1844-1924.
19 items (SC)
Papers of the French author, novelist, poet, playwright. 1 autograph ms. poem; 18 outgoing letters, 17 of which are addressed to Jean-Paul Oury.
149790
Biographical History
Anatole France (1844-1924) was a French novelist, essayist, poet, and critic who won the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1921.
Born François-Anatole Thibault in Paris on April 16, 1844, Anatole France was the son of Antoinette Galas and François-Noël Thibault, a bookseller and publisher. As a result of his father's profession, France grew up surrounded by books. He attended the Collège Saint-Stanislas from 1855 to 1862. He left the college in 1862 to begin studying independently and earned his baccalaureate degree in 1864. In 1877, France married Valérie Guérin de Sauville, with whom he had one daughter, Suzanne. The couple divorced in 1893. In 1920, France was remarried to Emma Laprevotte. France went on to have a prosperous literary career, winning the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1921. The prize was awarded "in recognition of his brilliant literary achievements, characterized as they are by a nobility of style, a profound human sympathy, grace, and a true Gallic temperament" (The Nobel Foundation, http://nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/literature/laureates/1921/index.html). He died in October 1924.
Selected Works
1859 La Légende de Sainte Radegonde, reine de France
1881 Le Crime de Sylvestre Bonnard, membre de l'Institut (The Crime of Sylvestre Bonnard)
1890 "Le Jongleur de Notre-Dame," (Our Lady's Juggler), published in Gaulois Thaïs
1891 "Le Procurateur de Judée" ("The Procurator of Judea"), published in La Temps
1893 Les Opinions de M. Jérôme Coignard (The Opinions of Jérôme Coignard) La Rôtisserie de la reine Pédauque (The Queen Pedauque)
1894 Le Jardin d'Epicure (The Gardens of Epicurus) Le Lys rouge (The Red Lily)
1895 Le Puits de Sainte Claire (The Well of Santa Clara)
1899 L'Anneau d'améthyste (The Amethyst Ring)
1901 L'Affaire Crainquebille Monsieur Bergeret à Paris (Monsieur Bergeret in Paris)
1905 Sur la pierre blanche (The White Stone)
1908 L'Ile des pingouins (Penguin Island) Vie de Jeanne d'Arc (Joan of Arc), 2 volumes
1909 Les Sept Femmes de la Barbe-Bleue et autres contes merveilleux (The Seven Wives of Bluebeard, and Other Marvellous Tales)
1912 La Comédie de celui qui épousa une femme muette (The Man Who Married A Dumb Wife) Les Dieux ont soif (The Gods Are Athirst)
1914 La Révolte des anges (The Revolt of the Angels)
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Anatole France Collection comprises 17 letters and two manuscripts of the French novelist, essayist, poet, and critic (1844-1924). Originating mainly from France's home, La Bechellerie in St. Cyr-Sur-Loire, 15 of the letters are addressed to architect Jean-Paul Oury. The content of the letters ranges from discussions of France's home and its furnishings to political analysis of the First World War. The letters also contain frequent mention of Emma Laprevotte who became the second Madame France in 1920, the year before her husband was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into two series: Correspondence and Writings. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- French; France, Anatole, 1844-1924 -- Correspondence.; Oury, Jean-Paul.; Authors, French.; French literature -- 19th century.; French literature -- 20th century.; Novelists, French.; Poets, French.; Letters (correspondence); Manuscripts for publication.; Authors.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 07 May 1915 (Sc 131)
  - 27 May 1915 (Sc 131)
  - 25 Apr 1916 (Sc 131)
  - 05 May 1916 (Sc 131)
  - 05 May 1916 (Sc 131)
  - 11 Dec 1916 (Sc 131)
  - 23 Jan 1917, 2 items (Sc 131)
  - 13 Feb 1917 (Sc 131)
  - 07 May 1917 (Sc 131)
  - 03 Jul 1917 (Sc 131)
  - 21 Sep 1917 (Sc 131)
  - 22 Sep 1917 (Sc 131)
  - 09 Oct 1917 (Sc 131)
  - undated, 4 items (Sc 131)
- Writings
  - Commentary on Gustave Nadaud, 1870s (Sc 131)
  - "Le mauvais ouvrier", undated; autographed manuscript poem (Sc 131)